So now let's talk about Beanstalk.
So when we have deployed a web application in AWS,
we typically follow a architecture
called a 3-tier architecture.
So our users talk to a load balancer
that could be in multiple available zones.
Then the load balancer will forward traffic
to multiple EC2 instances managed by
an auto scaling scaling group.
And then these EC2 instances need to store data somewhere
so they will use a database such as Amazon RDS
for a relational database to read and write data.
And if they need to have an in-memory database
for an in-memory cache, then they can also use ElastiCache
to store a retrieve the session data or the cached data.
Now this architecture is something
we can easily reproduce manually.
We can also reproduce it on AWS through CloudFormation,
but there is a better way.
So when you're a developer on AWS,
you don't want to be managing infrastructure,
you just want to be deploying code, okay?
You don't want to be able to configure all the databases,
the load balancers, et cetera,
and you wanna make sure that whatever you're doing scales.
And as we saw, most web applications will have the same
or similar architecture with a load balancer
and an auto scaling group.
So as a developer on AWS, all that you want to do
is to run your code.
Possibly you want to run your code
for different applications and environments the same way.
So there comes Elastic Beanstalk.
So Elastic Beanstalk is a developer centric view
of deploying an application on AWS.
And behind Beanstalk
we have the same components we've seen before.
So your EC2 instances, your auto scaling group,
your Elastic Load Balancer, your RDS database, et cetera.
But in Beanstalk, it's a developer centric view.
So it's one view that's easy to make sense of
with everything in it.
And we still have control over the configuration
of all the components, but it is all within Beanstalk.
So Beanstalk from a cloud perspective
is a platform as a service or PaaS
because we just worry about the code.
So to summarize, we saw infrastructure as a service,
so IaaS.
We saw platform as a service for Beanstalk, PaaS,
and then we're going to see software as a service
for other services on AWS.
So using Beanstalk is free,
but you're going to pay for the underlying instances.
So Elastic Beanstalk is a managed service.
That means that all the EC2 instance configuration
and operating system will be handled by Beanstalk itself.
The deployment strategy can be configured,
but again, the deployment itself
is going to be performed by Elastic Beanstalk.
All the capacity provisioning through an auto scaling group
and load balancing are done by Beanstalk.
And the application health monitoring
and responsiveness is also included
in the Beanstalk dashboard.
So what is your responsibility as a developer?
Well, just the application code,
and that makes Elastic Beanstalk
a very developer friendly service.
There are three architecture models with Elastic Beanstalk.
The first one is single instant deployment,
which is good for development environment,
but if you wanna scale up, you can have a load balancer
and an ASG, which is going to be great for production
or pre-production web applications.
And finally, if you want to have non-web apps in production,
for example, workers, you have an option to only have
an auto scaling group on as a standalone.
Beanstalk can be used to support many platforms.
For example, Go, Java, as well .NET, Node.js, PHP,
Python, Ruby, Packer, Docker, Multi Docker,
and Preconfigured Docker.
You don't need to remember this for the exam,
but as you can see, Beanstalk supports a lot of ways
to deploy your application, including Docker
and many programming languages.
Finally, a question that may come up in the exam
is around health monitoring.
So Beanstalk does have a full monitoring suite available
within the service itself.
And so there's going to be a health agent
on each EC2 instance within Beanstalk
that is going to push metrics to CloudWatch.
And then within Beanstalk you can view these metrics,
do some monitoring and so on.
But it will also check for application health
and will publish health events.
So these are just a bunch of screenshots that I've gotten
to really show you that Beanstalk
is a way to do health monitoring for your applications.
So now I really want to give you an idea
of how Elastic Beanstalk works.
So we'll see you in the next lecture for the hands-on
to give you a concrete demo.